So let's start setting up a nextJS project, you can find all the instructions on that github page
Yani bir nextJS projesi kurmaya balayalm, o github sayfasndaki tm talimatlar bulabilirsin ve bu
and that is a great place to dive deeper. As you can see there, nextjs in the latest version at the
daha derine dalmak iin harika bir yer. Grdnz gibi, en son srmde yer alan
point of time I'm recording this requires react 16 which under the hood introduced some breaking changes
nextJs'ler bunu kaydediyorum. Bu, 16'nn altnda kaputun altnda baz krlma deiikliklerini tantt ve kurs
and which is the version we used throughout the course.
boyunca kullandmz versiyon olan tepkiyi gerektiriyor.
So we're fine, we'll be using that version here too
Biz de iyiyiz, bu srm burada
and now let's install nextjs,
da kullanacaz ve imdi
this package with this command, as you see you also still install react and react-dom.
de bujs ile bu paketi kuralm, bu paketi hala tepkime ve tepkime yklyorsunuz.
Now to run this, you need an empty project
imdi bunu altrmak iin, bo bir projeye
and here I got one loaded in my IDE already,
ihtiyacnz var ve burada IDE'mde bir tane ykl
the only thing I have here is a gitignore file because I'll be using git.
var, burada kullanacam tek ey bir gitignore dosyas nk git'i kullanacam.
Now first of all to be able to run npm commands, we need to put this project under control of npm, you
imdi her eyden nce npm komutlarn altrabilmemiz iin, bu projeyi npm kontrol altna almalyz, bunu
do this by running npm init, then you are asked a couple of questions which you can simply answer with
npm init'i altrarak yaparsnz, o zaman sadece enter'a basarak sadece evet ile cevaplayabileceiniz
yes by just hitting enter. Once you went through all these questions,
birka soru sorulur. . Btn bu sorular inceledikten
you get a package.json file which is used to manage the dependencies.
sonra bir paket alrsnz. bamllklar ynetmek iin kullanlan json dosyas.
I do talk about creating this file in a bit more detail in the module where we create our own project
Bu dosyay, kendi projemizi oluturduumuz modlde biraz daha ayrntl olarak
set up from scratch.
oluturmaktan bahsediyorum.
Now we can run the command you saw on the github page here, npm install --save with these three packages,
imdi burada github sayfasnda grdnz komutu altrabiliriz, npm install --save ile bu  pakette
next, react and react-dom
ykleme yapn, sonra tepki
because nextjs is a library building app on react,
verin ve tepki verin, nk nextjs tepki veren bir ktphane
it gives you extra features but behind the scenes or also from a code perspective what you're going
oluturma uygulamasdr, size ekstra zellikler sunar ancak sahnelerin arkasnda ya da
to write, it's still all react.
yazacanz bir kod perspektifinden, hala tepki veriyor.
Once this command finished and all these packages are installed in their latest versions, we can go back
Bu komut bittiinde ve tm bu paketler son srmlerinde yklendikten sonra, daha fazla
to the github repository to find more instructions.
ynerge bulmak iin github deposuna geri dnebiliriz.
We should now add this scripts section to packaged.json
imdi bu komut dosyalarn blmlere paketlenmi olarak eklemeliyiz. json, hadi
so let's do this, in the package.json file, we actually have a script section, we can replace it with the
bunu yapalm, pakette. json dosyas, aslnda bir komut dosyas
one we just grabbed from our github file here,
blmmz var, biz sadece burada bizim github dosyasndan aldmz ile deitirebiliriz, bu yzden betik
so script should be added like this.
buna benzer ekilde eklenmelidir.
With that, we can start using it
Bununla birlikte, kullanmaya balayabiliriz
and now that we have that important file system thing
ve imdi bahsettiim nemli dosya
I was talking about, in nextjs, the file system is our main API,
sistemi eylerine sahibiz, sonraki sistemlerde, dosya sistemi bizim
we don't use react router with nextjs to create routes and allow the user to visit /auth, /user
ana API'mzdr, rota oluturmak ve kullancya izin vermek iin nextjs ile reaktif ynlendirici kullanmayz /
and so on,
auth, /
instead we create folders and files to reflect our URLs in the file system and nextJS, the package
user vb. ziyaret etmek yerine, dosya sistemimizdeki ve nextJS'deki URL'leri yanstacak klasrleri ve dosyalar olutururuz, paket bunu otomatik olarak
will automatically parse that and use its own internal router to handle all the heavy lifting.
ayrtrr ve tm ar ykleri ilemek iin kendi i ynlendiricisini kullanr.
Now along the way, it pre-renders the content we load as pages on the server, it automatically code splits,
imdi, yol boyunca, yklediimiz ierii sunucuda sayfalar olarak nceden oluturuyor, blcleri otomatik olarak kodluyoruz, bylece
so lazy loads that, all of that out of the box without us configuring anything.
tembel olmayan ykler, bizden hibir ey yapmadan kutudan kt.
That is why next is such a great package and could be worth a look in your next project,
te bu yzden bu kadar harika bir paket ve bir sonraki projenize gz atmaya
a lot of stuff is just working out of the box there at the price of having to keep a certain file structure.
deer olabilir, bir ok ey sadece belirli bir dosya yapsna sahip olmak zorunda kald iin kutudan kmaktadr.
That file structure is mostly about that pages folder,
Bu dosya yaps ounlukla bu sayfalar
let's create it. You create it directly in the root folder next to node modules and the other files here,
klasryle ilgili, onu oluturalm. Dm modllerinin ve dier dosyalarn yannda
so there, you create a new folder pages and in there, you now create your javascript files which will
bulunan kk klasrde dorudan oluturursunuz, bylece yeni bir klasr sayfas oluturursunuz
be react component which will hold and export react components and these file names
ve burada, bileenlerin tepki bileenlerini tutacak ve da aktaracanz javascript dosyalarnz oluturursunuz. Bu dosya adlar
now define the different paths you have. You can also have a subfolder like auth there
imdi sahip olduunuz farkl yollar tanmlar. Ayrca oradaki gibi bir alt klasre
and in there add for example user.js, you would reach this file at your domain/auth/user,
sahip olabilirsiniz ve orada rnein kullanc ekleyin. js, eer bu dizini isimlendirirseniz, bu dosyaya etki
if you name this index.js, you would reach it at /auth.
alannz / auth / user adresinden ularsnz. js, ona / auth'a ularsn.
Let's also add an index.js file under the pages folder,
Ayrca bir dizin ekleyelim. sayfalar klasrnn altnda js
now we have something like example.com/ and would reach that file and /auth and would reach
dosyas, imdi rnek gibi bir ey var. com / ve bu dosyaya ve / auth'a ular ve
that file.
bu dosyaya ular.
Now lets add a component in both
imdi hem bir bileene hem
and typically here, you use functional components but of course you can also use stateful ones with the
de tipik olarak buraya bir bileen ekleyelim, ilevsel bileenleri kullanyorsunuz, ancak devleti ynetmeniz
class keywords in case you need to manage state.
gerektiinde, durumsal olanlar snf anahtarlaryla da kullanabilirsiniz.
So let's create a functional one here,
O zaman burada ilevsel bir
I'll name this indexPage, the name is up to you though
tane oluturalm, bu indexPage ismini vereceim, isim size kalm, ve
and you know that syntax here, where you could receive props, return something.
burada szdizimini biliyorsunuz, burada sahne alabiliyorsunuz, bir eyler dndrebiliyorsunuz.
Now what I'll do is all import react from react so just like you learned it in this course, that doesn't
imdi yapacam ey, bu reaksiyonda rendikleriniz gibi reaksiyonun tepkimeye girmesidir, bu deimez, nk
change because we're still using jsx here,
hala burada jsx kullanyoruz, henz
well not yet but we'll do so in a second
deil ama bir saniye sonra
and I export indexPage as a default.
yapacaz. export indexPage varsaylan olarak.
That's important,
Bu nemli,
you still need to export this otherwsie nextjs can't do a thing with that.
yine de u dierleri ihra etmelisin, aksi halde bununla bir ey yapamazsn.
So now let's simply add some code
yleyse imdi bir
here, like a div where we say h1 the main page, like this. Now I'll copy all that code and put it into
kod ekleyelim, burada ana sayfa olan h1 dediimiz bir div gibi. imdi tm kodu kopyalayp
the other index.js file, I'll name this authIndexPage and of course therefore export this constant
dier dizine koyacam. js dosyas, bu authIndexPage adn vereceim ve tabiki bu
and there, I'll say the auth index page.
sabiti de da aktaracam, auth indeks sayfasn syleyeceim.
Now let's save that and
imdi bunu
now let's execute one of the scripts we added, dev.
kaydedelim ve imdi eklediimiz scriptlerden birini uygulayalm, dev.
Now if you run npm run dev, this will spin up a development server building your application and server
imdi npm run dev'i altrrsanz, bu, uygulama ve sunucu tarafnz gelitiren bir gelitirme sunucusunu dndrecek ve bu
side rendering it also giving you stuff like hot reloading so a really
da size gerekten gzel bir gelitirme ortam olan scak yeniden
nice development environment.
ykleme gibi eyler sunacaktr.
If you now go back to the browser, you can actually load this in a new tab under localhost:3000,
imdi taraycnza geri dnyorsanz, bunu localhost: 3000 altnda yeni bir sekmede ykleyebilirsiniz. Burada,
there you should see your page and if you now go to /auth you see the auth index page.
sayfanz grmeniz gerekir ve imdi / auth'a giderseniz, auth index sayfasn grrsnz.
So without us setting up any routing, we can load these two different components as pages and as I said,
Bu yzden herhangi bir ynlendirme kurmadan, bu iki farkl bileeni sayfalar olarak ykleyebiliriz ve dediim gibi,
these components doesn't have to be functional components,
bu bileenlerin ilevsel bileenler olmas gerekmez, bunlar
they could be class based components too.
da snf tabanl bileenler olabilir.